<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" ".//reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<!-- WK: Set category, IPR, docName -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ekwk-capport-rfc7710bis-01"
     ipr="trust200902"
     updates="7710"
     >
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes"?>

  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <!--c WK: Set long title. -->

    <title abbrev="DHCP Captive-Portal">Captive-Portal Identification in DHCP
    / RA</title>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Erik Kline" initials="E." surname="Kline">
      <organization>Google Japan</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Roppongi 6-10-1, 44th Floor</street>

          <country>Japan</country>

          <code>106-6144</code>

          <city>Minato, Tokyo</city>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <email>ek@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2018"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>In many environments offering short-term or temporary Internet access
      (such as coffee shops), it is common to start new connections in a
      captive portal mode. This highly restricts what the customer can do
      until the customer has authenticated.</t>

      <t>This document describes a DHCP option (and a Router Advertisement
      (RA) extension) to inform clients that they are behind some sort of
      captive-portal device, and that they will need to authenticate to get
      Internet access. It is not a full solution to address all of the issues
      that clients may have with captive portals; it is designed to be used in
      larger solutions. The method of authenticating to, and interacting with
      the captive portal is out of scope of this document.</t>

      <t> [ This document is being collaborated on in Github at:
      https://github.com/wkumari/draft-ekwk-capport-rfc7710bis. The most
      recent version of the document, open issues, etc should all be available
      here. The authors (gratefully) accept pull requests. Text in square
      brackets will be removed before publication. ]</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In many environments, users need to connect to a captive-portal
      device and agree to an Acceptable Use Policy (AUP) and / or provide
      billing information before they can access the Internet. It is
      anticipated that the IETF will work on a more fully featured protocol at
      some point, to ease interaction with Captive Portals. Regardless of how
      that protocol operates, it is expected that this document will provide
      needed functionality because the client will need to know when it is
      behind a captive portal and how to contact it.</t>

      <t>In order to present users with the payment or AUP pages, the
      captive-portal device has to intercept the user's connections and
      redirect the user to the captive portal, using methods that are very
      similar to man-in-the-middle (MITM) attacks. As increasing focus is
      placed on security, and end nodes adopt a more secure stance, these
      interception techniques will become less effective and/or more
      intrusive.</t>

      <t>This document describes a DHCP (<xref target="RFC2131"/>) option
      (Captive-Portal) and an IPv6 Router Advertisement (RA) (<xref
      target="RFC4861"/>) extension that informs clients that they are behind
      a captive-portal device and how to contact it.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="option" title="The Captive-Portal Option">
      <t>The Captive Portal DHCP / RA Option informs the client that it is
      behind a captive portal and provides the URI to access an authentication
      page. This is primarily intended to improve the user experience by
      getting them to the captive portal faster; for the foreseeable future,
      captive portals will still need to implement the interception techniques
      to serve legacy clients, and clients will need to perform probing to
      detect captive portals.</t>

      <t>In order to support multiple "classes" of clients (e.g. IPv4 only,
      IPv6 only with DHCPv6 (<xref target="RFC3315"/>), IPv6 only with RA) the
      captive portal can provide the URI via multiple methods (IPv4 DHCP, IPv6
      DHCP, IPv6 RA). The captive portal operator should ensure that the URIs
      handed out are equivalent to reduce the chance of operational problems.
      The maximum length of the URI that can be carried in IPv4 DHCP is 255
      bytes, so URIs longer than 255 bytes should not be used in IPv6 DHCP or
      IPv6 RA.</t>

      <t>In all variants of this option, the URI SHOULD be that of the
      captive portal API endpoint, conforming to the recommendations for such
      URIs [cite:API] (i.e. the URI SHOULD contain a DNS name and SHOULD
      reference a secure transport, e.g. https). A captive portal MAY do
      content negotiation [citation?] and attempt to redirect clients querying
      without an explicit indication of support for the captive portal API
      content type (i.e. without application/capport+json listed explicitly
      anywhere within an Accepts header [citation]). In so doing, the captive
      portal SHOULD redirect the client to the value associated with the
      "user-portal-url" API key.</t>

      <t>The URI SHOULD NOT contain an IP address literal.</t>

      <t>The URI parameter is not null terminated.</t>

      <t>Networks with no captive portals MAY explicitly indicate this condition
      by using this option with the IANA-assigned URI for this purpose (see
      <xref target="ietf_params_capport-unrestricted"/>). Clients observing the
      URI value "urn:ietf:params:capport-unrestricted" MAY forego time-consuming
      forms of captive portal detection.</t>

      <section anchor="dhcpv4opt" title="IPv4 DHCP Option">
        <t>The format of the IPv4 Captive-Portal DHCP option is shown
        below.<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[    Code   Len           Data
   +------+------+------+------+------+--   --+-----+
   | code | len  |  URI                  ...        |
   +------+------+------+------+------+--   --+-----+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Code: The Captive-Portal DHCPv4 Option (160) (one octet)</t>

            <t>Len: The length, in octets of the URI.</t>

            <t>URI: The URI for the captive portal API endpoint to which
            the user should connect (encoded following the rules in <xref
            target="RFC3986"/>).</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="dhcpv6opt" title="IPv6 DHCP Option">
        <t>The format of the IPv6 Captive-Portal DHCP option is shown below.
        <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |          option-code          |          option-len           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   .                      URI (variable length)                    .
   |                              ...                              |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>option-code: The Captive-Portal DHCPv6Option (103) (two
            octets)</t>

            <t>option-len: The length, in octets of the URI.</t>

            <t>URI: The URI for the captive portal API endpoint to which
            the user should connect (encoded following the rules in <xref
            target="RFC3986"/>).</t>
          </list>See <xref target="RFC7227"/>, Section 5.7 for more examples
        of DHCP Options with URIs.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="v6ndopt" title="The Captive-Portal IPv6 RA Option">
        <t>This section describes the Captive-Portal Router Advertisement
        option.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Type      |     Length    |              URI              .
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               .
   .                                                               .
   .                                                               .
   .                                                               .
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            Figure 2: Captive-Portal RA Option Format]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Type">37</t>

            <t hangText="Length">8-bit unsigned integer. The length of the
            option (including the Type and Length fields) in units of 8
            bytes.</t>

            <t hangText="URI">The URI for the captive portal API endpoint to
            which the user should connect. This MUST be padded with
            NULL (0x00) to make the total option length (including the
            Type and Length fields) a multiple of 8 bytes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="linkrel" title="The Captive-Portal Link Relation Type">
      <t>Some captive portal network deployments may be unable to change, or
      unwilling to risk changing, the network infrastructure necessary to use
      any of the above options. In such deployments, when clear text HTTP
      intercept and redirection are used, a Link relation header
      (<xref target="RFC8288"/>, Section 3.3) MAY be inserted to convey to a
      HTTP client (user agent) the associated Captive Portal API URI.
      </t>
      <t>HTTP user agents MUST ignore this link relation in any context other
      than when explicitly probing to detect the presence of a captive portal.
      Failure to do so could allow an attacker to inject a Captive Portal API
      URI other than the correct URI for a given network or for networks where
      there is no captive portal present at all.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document requests two new IETF URN protocol parameter
      (<xref target="RFC3553"/>) entries.</t>

      <t>Thanks IANA!</t>

      <section anchor="ietf_params_registration"
               title="IETF params Registration">

        <section anchor="ietf_params_capport-unrestricted"
                 title="Registry name: Captive Portal Unrestricted Identifier">
          <t>Registry name: Captive Portal Unrestricted Identifier</t>

          <t>URN: urn:ietf:params:capport-unrestricted</t>

          <t>Specification: RFC TBD (this document)</t>

          <t>Repository: RFC TBD (this document)</t>

          <t>Index value: Only one value is defined (see URN above). No
          hierarchy is defined and therefore no sub-namespace registrations are
          possible.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="ietf_params_capport-api"
                 title="Registry name: Captive Portal API Link Relation Type">
          <t>Registry name: Captive Portal API Link Relation Type</t>

          <t>URN: urn:ietf:params:capport-api</t>

          <t>Specification: RFC TBD (this document)</t>

          <t>Repository: RFC TBD (this document)</t>

          <t>Index value: Only one value is defined (see URN above). No
          hierarchy is defined and therefore no sub-namespace registrations are
          possible.</t>
        </section>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>An attacker with the ability to inject DHCP messages could include
      this option and so force users to contact an address of his choosing. As
      an attacker with this capability could simply list himself as the
      default gateway (and so intercept all the victim's traffic); this does
      not provide them with significantly more capabilities, but because this
      document removes the need for interception, the attacker may have an
      easier time performing the attack. As the operating systems and
      application that make use of this information know that they are
      connecting to a captive-portal device (as opposed to intercepted
      connections) they can render the page in a sandboxed environment and
      take other precautions, such as clearly labeling the page as untrusted.
      The means of sandboxing and user interface presenting this information
      is not covered in this document - by its nature it is implementation
      specific and best left to the application and user interface
      designers.</t>

      <t>Devices and systems that automatically connect to an open network
      could potentially be tracked using the techniques described in this
      document (forcing the user to continually authenticate, or exposing
      their browser fingerprint). However, similar tracking can already be
      performed with the standard captive portal mechanisms, so this technique
      does not give the attackers more capabilities.</t>

      <t>Captive portals are increasingly hijacking TLS connections to force
      browsers to talk to the portal. Providing the portal's URI via a DHCP or
      RA option is a cleaner technique, and reduces user expectations of being
      hijacked - this may improve security by making users more reluctant to
      accept TLS hijacking, which can be performed from beyond the network
      associated with the captive portal.</t>

      <t>By simplifying the interaction with the captive portal systems, and
      doing away with the need for interception, we think that users will be
      less likely to disable useful security safeguards like DNSSEC
      validation, VPNs, etc. In addition, because the system knows that it is
      behind a captive portal, it can know not to send cookies, credentials,
      etc. By handing out a URI using which is protected with TLS, the captive
      portal operator can attempt to reassure the user that the captive portal
      is not malicious.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document is a -bis of RFC7710. Thanks to all of the original
      authors (Warren Kumari, Olafur Gudmundsson, Paul Ebersman, Steve Sheng),
      and original contributors.</t>

      <t>Also thanks to the CAPPORT WG for all of the discussion and
      improvements.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2131'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2939'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3315'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3553'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3986'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4861'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7227'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8288'?>
    </references>

    <section title="Changes / Author Notes.">
      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section before publication ]</t>

      <t>From initial to -00.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Import of RFC7710.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
